So now that you've learned about the different
types of hazards and risks that may be present in
the workplace and why it's important to eliminate
them, let's take a look at a risk assessment
document, which will allow you to identify the
different types of hazards, the potential risks,
who it may, harm, and how these can be resolved.
So I have on the screen in front of me, a
simple risk assessment form you may find a
more Complicated version within your workplace.
It all depends on the type of work that's
being carried out and the environment that
it's being carried out in but this would
be appropriate for most business places.
So as you can see at the very top, it's asking
me to put my name in so the assessment's
carried out by and then enter my name, and
then the date the assessment was carried out.
It's then looking for me to fill it in and put
down what are the hazards that I've found, the
potential risks that could be caused from the
hazard, who that may harm, and what action is
needed  to reduce or eliminate the hazard risk.
So I have an example workplace on
this screen here, and as you can see,
this is an example of  a busy office
environment and there's a lot going on.
Quite a lot of people work in there and
there are several potential hazards within
this example and I'm just going to pick
out a couple, just to give you an example.
And the first one I'm going to look at is this
one here, and this is workstation ergonomics.
Now, as you can see, the person using this
computer the computer screen is off to the left,
which is incorrect there's definitely something
wrong there and also, so the potential for that is
that that person could be, causing back problems
or neck problems and straining to see because of
the, the unnatural way that is having to turn,
or he's having to turn to look at the screen.
So if we go back to the actual
risk assessment document, so.
The first thing is what are the hazards?
And so pop that in there so the, the, it's a
workstation ergonomics theres poor desk layout.
So what are the potential
risks that could be caused?
And this is back or neck injury or strain.
There may be others, but those are the two
most common, that ones that would occur from
this type of work in, in looking, having to
look constantly to the left at the screen.
So who might be harmed thats anyone using
the equipment on that desk and so what
action is needed to reduce the hazard risk?
A display screen assessment would be useful,
and the layout of the equipment on the desk
needs to be checked and correctly set up so that
whoever's using it is not gonna have the risk
of having strains to the neck or back injury
when they're using the equipment on that desk.
So let's have a look for another one, and so
the next one, I'll just have a look at this
gentleman here who's carrying some boxes.
First thing there is he can't see over the
top of the boxes and those boxes, they may
be light, but they do look rather large.
So we'll have a look at that and a
person carrying too much at once.
So let's see how we would enter
that onto the risk assessment.
So what is the hazard carrying too much
weight and the potential risk is that
there's a risk of back injury of falling.
And so who might be harmed and how?
So the individuals counting the boxes or anybody
else who may be hit if the boxes fall onto them.
So how could that be resolved?
So the first thing is that it should be
ensured that anybody carrying boxes and that
around the office, this should be given, the
training on lifting and handing, and also
what is the appropriate size and weight.
So let's take another look and see if we can spot
any others and I'm going to pick this one up here.
There's a printer on the floor in the corner, and
it's been placed on the floor instead of a table.
So again, how would we fill
in our risk assessment.
So the print has been placed on the floor.
So what is the potential risk from that?
And it's the potential for injury
when walking past the printer.
And that is also the possible contact with
water when the office is being cleaned.
So the printer could have water going inside it
because it's on the floor if somebody's cleaning
the floor, that water could get in there.
So who might be harmed?
So all staff, anybody who's walking past the
printer may bang into it with their legs so
obviously injury to legs and also all staff if
the components within the printer become wet
that's also the potential for electrocution.
So how can it be resolved?
Quite simply, the printer needs to
be placed on a desk or a dedicated
printer stand to keep it off the floor.
So as you can see, filling out a risk assessment
is quite a straightforward, logical process.
You would do a visual assessment of the,
the workplace, look for any hazards, what
the risks are, who it may harm, and then
what needs to be done to reduce that.
So now that you've had a look at that, in
your assessment you'll be required to carry
out a, a risk assessment yourself, and you've
been provided with a scenario similar to
the one that I've used on the screen there.
So you need to go in there, have a look,
identify what other hazards, and then fill in
the document similar to what I've done here.